thank you
hello and welcome it's March 23 2023 and
we're here in active live stream 53.1
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
this is a recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn more about
the Institute and learning groups and
projects
we're here in academstream 53.1 and we
are discussing a dyad of papers
we are discussing snakes and ladders in
paleoanthropology by
Hector Carl and Michael welcome Carl and
we're discussing to copy or not to copy
with Hector and Michael previously in
53.0 we Dean and I provided some
background and context on these papers
and today in 53.1
first we will all say hello
then we will feature a presentation by
Michael Walker and following the
presentation we'll have a discussion and
see where it goes so with no further Ado
we will all say hello to the non-authors
first then the authors concluding with
Michael and leading into the
presentation so
I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and it was a great
fun and learning experience to work on
the dot zero so I'm really excited to
continue in the dot one today
to Dean
thanks Daniel I'm Dean I'm here in
Calgary um
I guess the only thing I want to just
highlight today is the fact that it's a
32323 and I I I love that bouncing back
and forth between those uh those two
quantities so I'm really excited and I
will pass this to Hector
okay hello I'm Hector manrique and I
will just summarize with bromy here
basically I graduated in Psychology that
was in Spain and then I did my PhD in
psychobiology so I came to learn the
biological basis of behavior
um then I recycled into a comparative
psychology when I joined the max plan
Institute of for evolution and
anthropology in Leipzig I was lucky that
I could work with Joseph Kai and that
his supervision and then I had the
opportunity to work with the four
species of great apes and after that I I
came to know Michael in a confidence on
human evolution and we have been working
together ever since we are now good
friends and also colleagues and that's
it basically
thank you Hector and Carl if you'd like
to say hello
please
so my name is Carl fiston I'm a
professor of neuroscience at University
College London
um and a colleague of our sort of main
speakers today but I've never seen in
person uh but now at least I have seen
you uh virtually they're very nice to
meet you
great thank you Carl
Michael
the floor is yours I'm very pleased
you'll say hello to Carl uh whom I've
not yet met personally but we're now
meeting visually virtually
um
I'm a retired professor at University of
Washington in Spain
I'm getting live ancient I should be 82
years out tomorrow but anyway that
doesn't stop me if I'm digging up
Neanderthal skeletons and even earlier
things here in Spain
um I'm very pleased to be presenting
this
it's a case of
the dog that didn't bark in the night so
um whenever you want me to begin I Can
Begin Daniel
yes the uh slide is up and it is all you
well this is really
a paper which we have out on sign
archive in the version in an earlier
version it's now been modified for a
different journal to the one that was
originally intended but the presentation
is in order to make a complicated uh
subject fairly simple to comprehend
I call it Snakes and Ladders because
stuff appears to disappears and
reappears throughout human evolution
over the past at least two million years
if not before and the question is why is
there not a continuous trajectory let's
move on to the next one Daniel
right the traditional view is the
received wisdom is looking at
anthropology can tell us from the
outside and there are two basic
methodologies one based on geology and
Darwinism which gives us one view of
what it is all about and another view
down on the bottom right is all based on
what
modern people do and what modern Apes do
and it's all by so-called analogy let's
move on to the next one
both of these have drawbacks uh I won't
go into this in detail you're welcome to
take these slides away provided you
don't publish them because they do
include some materials on from other
sources which I haven't um acknowledged
formally but the drawbacks to the to
Darwinism is really the difficulty of
being able to
uh prove anything in the past by in its
own terms
um okay we can accept it as being a
valid way of explaining natural
phenomena and evolution the drawback to
using modern analogies is the spatio
temporal
incumblensivability in commensurability
with regard to the regular
irregularities and irregular
regularities of which things appear
disappear and reappear throughout the
pleistocene record and indeed prehistory
in general let's move on to the next one
so instead of looking at it from the
outside let's look at it from the inside
and this has an advantage of
commensurability uh
and compatibility at the same time with
the gradual evolution of and within
species by natural selection and at the
same time with the documented behavior
of arganus hormone uh well this is from
uh cars and his colleagues latest book
I'm sure you all know it so let's move
on to the next one
right uh in the 1960s
some archaeologists were certainly
reflecting including some Cambridge fans
of mine on
the ostensive presence of irregular
regularities and regular irregularities
in the archaeological record and a
well-known one is the case of the wheel
wheels uh we use for Traction in um
Central Asia and the Middle East for
about 5 000 years ago they were invented
separately in mesoamerica of just over 2
000 years ago they weren't used for any
kind of practical purpose but just for
moving Effigies statues and toys around
and this season has been completely
independent inventions Okay so
let's say that surprising enactment with
stuff
was the exception in uh early humans
let's see if I can getting a little bit
tied up with two screens I'm working on
my own screen at the same time
uh
cognitive surprises
were probably disregarded in general
because
surprising spontaneous and excellent
with stuff distracted attention away
from daily routines
if we go back two million years ago when
Homer first appears from the earlier
um bipedal humans or human ancestors
we begin to see the
establishment of the Guinness Homer
especially in Africa
and
I'm sure that spontaneous enactment is
stuff
certainly
occurred innumerable times without
gaining any Foothills as technological
or cultural if you like communal
behavioral Traditions passed down to
generation and Innovation because this
is unlikely if we take a period let's
say from two million years ago even to
an even to half a million years ago
that's one and a half million years
that's 60 000 generations of you
consider one generation as lasting 25
years it's most unlikely that things
could be handed down from father to son
over sixty thousand Generations
so let's take a different take on this
let's go back to look at it from the
inside
upon considerations of the free energy
principle and active influence
it follows an actual inference underpins
biological behavior that has exploratory
or epistemic and exploitative or
pragmatic aspects sensitive respectively
to ambiguity and risk enabling epistemic
and ambiguity resolving responses to
support pragmatic reward seeking ones
and therefore it is not implausible that
the snakes and ladders appearance
disappearance and reappearance of stuff
over let's say the past two million
years of the existence of organist
oh to know more than the extreme Rarity
with which unorthodox epistemic
exploration of possibly advantageous
opportunities
resulted from incipient albeit and
perceptibly evolving neurobiological
propensities uh in brains or
hierarchical mechanistic Minds to
generate exploitative pragmatic
attention by our active infants to
cognitive surprises from and towards
behavioral incidents which once
expressed more on to the next one so
let's forget about it let's move on to
the next one Daniel let's forget about
this uh how do I get from here to there
how do I get more Olympic lock to that's
their hand ax but spontaneously what
could provoke this okay let's move on
next slide
I excavated the size I am Excavating the
size almost a million years old which
has one hand ax remains of burning lots
of small stone tools so you can see some
burnt ones on the bottom left but then
this is the dog that didn't bark
why are there no more handouts why do we
only have one big Lodge by facial shape
that's cutting into all the hand X and
hundreds of tiny little tools people
don't ask that question
let's move on to the next one the
explain it away
boom people really didn't bother with
cutting up big animals they didn't need
big cutting tools
well that's one way of looking at it
prove it
people lost stuff and so there should be
more of these around but there's only
one well prove that
there's only one because people took
them away and use them elsewhere move
that the problem is this these so-called
interpretations only explain stuff away
could well have been a Valentine gift or
not next slide
so let's get back to
Snakes and Ladders we have fire at the
site there aren't too many sites with
fire either and again uh the general
assumption is that there was continuity
uh once yeah trouble with moving my
other
um
my other screen
how can I move this on excuse me a
moment uh my eyesight isn't all that
good these days
nope that's not doing it no doubt excuse
me one minute
um
so we have the the file as I just
mentioned and
I don't believe that suddenly fire was
brought to humans or invented and then
passed on from father to son
nor do I believe as we'll see in the
next slide that this was done along with
an expansion okay we'll have the next
one down here please
um
of these early Homo erectus moving from
Africa and outwards carrying a hand ax
carrying little Embers and spreading the
good news no next slide don't think it
worked like that stuff couldn't have
been passed on overall that period of
time over all that space this is not
commensurable with modern human or
modern ape Behavior
let's move on to the next one Daniel so
how do we begin We Begin by bashing
Stone in excellent with stuff and that
started over three million years ago we
know that next one please
and then we have another problem which
is that there is almost exponential
increase in stock artifacts made by
people and yet the brain as we know from
fossil evidence does not follow that
trajectory which is the red one the
brain increases and gradually flattens
out at the same time as the number of
stuff that people make increases or
almost exponentially let's have the next
one so here we have another problem to
try and solve
and one possibility which was pointed
out by the late professor Philip Tobias
uh is that as the brain increases we see
in the paleontal paleoanthological they
called an increase in the variation in
the volume of the brain suggesting
perhaps that there is some relaxation of
selection pressure as homo uh evolved
and we have the next
that's a point which is worth bearing in
mind
so let's think about
another way of how all this male men of
them happened
a methodological perspective grounded in
fundamental
biological and physical relationships
gives us a parsimonious Mosaic
deflationary account all these
appearances disappearances and
reappearances of Behavioral outcomes and
so-called skills now
Professor Nicholas steenbergen who was a
professor of zoology at Oxford and got a
Nobel Prize was fascinated with four
questions let's have the next slide and
see what those are you want to know how
we can
relate Evolution at four different
levels that of ontogeny and that of the
mechanisms the causation
that's a phylogeny and that of
adaptation or survival value and
these are related uh
sent via chronically and synchronically
as one can see from this little diagram
into also what might call proximate and
ultimate explanatory
um uh approaches
if we look at the problem in hand let's
have the next slide Daniel
um we can see that here we have in the
diacronic aspects Paleolithic behavior
in general in the synchronic one stuff
appearing at different times in the top
right
as far as ontogeny is concerned we have
something which I'll mention later on
but we need to make a big deal of it
that we know that there was a lack of
adolescent Growth work and a relatively
uh um
small brain in homoelect just one and a
half million years ago compared with
ours it's about two-thirds of the side
of ours
when we think of mechanisms here we come
to look at it from the inside
we have a matter of awareness involving
active influence the three energy
principle and variation of the energy
and we have what happens at the
neurophysiological level uh allowing a
complexity of behavior between hand and
and stuff and and so in this case or
stones
we have to involve matters such as
working memory long-term memory
perspective memory and indeed
um constructive memory
so how does all this time to phylogen
here we have a Snakes and Ladder model
based on the empirical evidence from the
past and we have survival value that
clearly existed because homologous
eventually gave rise to us next slide
please
so let's get back to Snakes and Ladders
here we have looking at lock and saying
how the hell do I get this hand
accomplish and now the next one and in
the same way with the next slide we have
the snakes and ladders a game of protons
and a random outcomes but but but next
slide please we are not dealing with
completely random outcomes there's a big
difference between on the one hand the
spatio temple snakes and that is game of
chance as if those of a dice alone
brought about appearance of
disappearances in their appearances by
group phenomena unrelated to responses
of the hierarchical mechanistic minds of
early homo and on the other hand a
hey snakes and that is analogy but
regular irregularities and irregular
regularities in the behavioral record
owing to individual idiosyncratical and
Orthodox activity and the receptivity to
it or not of an observing hierarchical
mechanistic mind whether it's for
non-lookup a bystander or that even the
South same man making the woman making
the handbags
okay let's move on to the next one and
here we begin to see
that the heterogeneous
composition of a picture of appearances
by chance alone disciplines is by chance
of their reappearances by chance alone
then is it useless as a model for making
predictions that can be compared or
contrasted with archaeological signings
of early paralytic science whereas our
preferred model by focusing on the
information theoretic and energetic
constraints on biological
neurobiological and psychosocial
Evolution affords as a picture that lets
us consider whether the model's Focus
could offer a rational interpretation of
the material black Ward and the zika of
the uneven distribution across the old
world things like stone hand access and
evidence of the tending of fire or even
visiting caves things that chimpanzees
and gorillas don't do between 2 million
and let's say 200 000 years ago in this
case 80 000 Generations okay let's move
on very quickly and the rest of it in
fact you're welcome to uh read for
yourselves rather than have me read it
out to you because basically
um you can take this away or copy it or
download it
what we are now arguing is that about a
million years ago adaptive Evolution was
underware of cerebral human
neurobiological propensities that
support prospective and constructive
memory in making artifacts or working
with stuff doing unusual unorthodox
themes together with short-term working
memory including that of the hands
haptic working memory long-term working
memory and long-term procedural and
episodic memory there's propensities
will find out genetic outcomes of
existential ontogenetic programs adapted
to the natural selection for satisfying
the bioenergetic requirements of
organisms our get us in particular
so
here we have the basis of our arguments
it is a small band of communicatively
challenged Homo erectus one member
spontaneous enactment often was went
unregarded disregarded
because regarded as useless pointless
and unhelpful to Gathering the food
requirements needed to surviving from
day to day
and we can refer the matter to the three
energy principle applied to ecological
nicheconstruction variation on your
orthology to use Professor efficient
phrase whereby selection of adaptive
actions organisms involves their
assessment of their Alternatives in
terms of the expected variation of three
energy expresses the combination of
epistemic and pragmatic affordances
so these early individuals a million and
a half years ago who experienced
cognitive surprises that's to say
prediction errors about effective uh
variational theology were unlikely to
introduce novel behaviors whether
affected or seen by them they could gain
a foothold in their Community before
those communicative skills have
developed in some groups that widened
their social scope for active influence
and involved by natural selection within
a shared framework of adapted prayer
beliefs favoring alignment of common
expectations and Joint activities that
affected their ecological niche well
that's the basis of our argument
of course it's no more as it were
fortified law or the future or within
the terms of the data from the past than
the Alternatives that I began with but
at least it makes rational coherent
sense and fits in with the uh darwinist
view of the evolution of species and
within species by natural selection
it is a more prosaic and deflation rate
argument than the ones that people
archaeologists and anthropologists like
to use and which I began with so
you can take this away and read it and
read it carefully what we're arguing is
about a million years ago uh
sorry can you move on Daniel
and again
so let's just uh stick with this
um
I think we can I think we can go through
this rather quickly move on to the next
one uh
uh yes sir right let's go let's go back
to a million and a half years ago let's
look at the stuff we know there's a
skeleton about
only nine years old according to uh
Professor Christopher the dean of
University College uh professor of
dental anatomy and he studied the teeth
and whilst at one time uh this
individual had the same height as myself
I'm about um I'm all the short
one meter 57
um
nevertheless although he had our adult
size he only he was only a child at nine
years old and his skull had almost
certainly stopped going it was only
two-thirds or less than the size of ours
but he was these people were clearly
making hand axes and lighting fires or
at least carrying file around it from
time to time and visiting caves we know
there was one in South Africa bomber
cave
and doing stuff that is sort of halfway
between what a chimp does and what our
modern primitive peoples are supposed to
have been able to do let's say ten
thousand or twenty thousand years ago
during the last ice age but there's a
big time difference here and when we
think about this kid
clearly he was developing much sooner
than we do he became an adult probably
before the age of 15 years old whereas
our brains are not fully formed for at
least another 10 years so this would
have limited let's have the next slide
um uh you can take these away and look
at that I don't I don't have to read all
this out in detail to you but in uh in
short
um
these people were precociously developed
and therefore much more limited they
would be behaving perhaps more like
let's say
um a modern I don't know four or
five-year-old child of modern adult
height and with a small brain well
they're not doing too badly if they kept
uh making uh things making stuff uh with
their hands doing things and then
forgetting about them because their main
purpose was to survive and they had to
eat and find something to eat and they
couldn't spend all their time in these
rather than productive activities so
let's say that um
let's take the active influence approach
to this and suggest that from a
perspective of the free energy principle
and active influence the differences uh
that we're seeing
contextualize The Experience dependent
learning and planning and influence on a
small scale but they reflect the
structural and neurobiological priors
that could be inherited by epigenetic
and genetic processes within the
hierarchically
mechanistic minds that were evolving and
which certainly were not the same as
those of modern chimpanzees and
guerrillas that don't do all these
things that even are Homo ancestors were
doing one and a half million years ago
well
Okay I accept that the absence of
evidence need not imply the evidence of
their absence but
that fails to satisfy most people or
many people particularly scientists like
ourselves
certainly uh the Darwin's argument had
Powerhouse power but if we
take a look at early human evolution
from the perspective of the free energy
principle our proposal invokes an
overarching methodological Paradigm
grounded in an existential principle
fundamental to the evolution of living
organisms and is consistent both with
the long periods of time and the vast
periods of space in the old world that
we are dealing with let's say 60 000 or
even 80 000 Generations across three
continents
and
nevertheless uh explain allows us to
interpret from the point of view of
natural selection what was going on
albeit imperceptibly slowly
by natural selection and adaptation
at least some of the irregular
regularities and regular irregularities
or phenomena attributable to Romeo in
the pleistocene record reflect the kinds
of claws of the anomalous behavioral
outcomes that doubtless occurred often
in the snakes and ladders model of
evolution in early members of organis
regardless of what species we want to
call their skeletal remains whether
neanderthals or the lectures modern homo
whatever
okay these are plausible uh outcomes of
behavior by individuals who fail to
maintain Orthodox behavioral responses
when faced with cognitive supplies and
people showed
almost certainly particularly in
neurobiological propensity to exploring
unorthodox possibilities a propensity
that's involved further in humans and in
great apes which are leak and like even
our very young children seem unable to
envisage how things might be as well as
how they actually are as the Canadian
psychologists and primatologist
Professor Ann Rustin has written and
with that I will end my little
introduction which I hope will explain
of all the complicated approach to
producing a novel interpretation of uh
how human behavior was evolving during a
very long period of time and across a
very large period of space on our planet
during the pleistocene thank you
thank you Michael yes that is the end of
the presentation
great
thank you for the presentation
we will now move into
discussion so I'm gonna
open up a blank page and then Hector
Carl and Dean please feel free to join
Dean first
I want to just first of all Michael I
don't know I'm not sure what your
stature is in person but after that
presentation you're a giant in my mind
so and that's that's not said out of
out of me needing to compliment you and
I think that thank you for the
presentation I'm curious now because the
approach that Daniel and I took was one
of trying to parameterize a space
between the two papers I'm curious now
what Hector thinks in terms of sort of
holding up that other that other side of
this set in particular with the paper on
to copy or not to copy and uh we might
Now sort of gain some depth perception
around things like zonu about its
surprisal now that we've had sort of the
introduction with the presentation that
Michael just shared
foreign
feel free to give a first comment okay
so you want me to comment on to copy or
not to copy on this one or how they
exactly yeah the Zone amount is
surprises in particular but yeah sort of
the groundwork that Michael has just
established okay perfect I would like to
start by thanking uh both uh Michael and
Carl for uh I mean this collaboration
because I think I was thinking in the
aphorism by Newton while activity to
Newton is not original from him of on
the shoulder of Giants and and I think I
feel like here I'm on this huge
intellect and and I feel very privileged
too so I want to thank them both and
Carl especially because he has been so
kind as to revise our two papers I mean
in one he's author but in the other he
revised it and give us very good uh
indications and advice to him very
grateful because we all know how busy he
is so it took the time to help us and
I'm very grateful and coming back to the
the papers the thing is that Michael
came up with this original idea of
explaining this appearance and
disappearance of hand access in terms of
the free energy principle
um
and when we were working on that paper I
thought that the same argument could
apply naturally to the case of gray
Daves and the thing that there was this
personally in grade 8's um
studies when they study this kind of
social transmission or culture or
commodative culture cumulative
technology and what's happened is that
there are many reports on chimpanzees
being innovative
meaning Innovative like they invent new
things new behaviors or new exploitation
Resources by applying new tools so there
are many instances of this but there is
a puzzle here as there is the other
puzzle with appearance and
disappearances of technology that there
is no cumulative technology so this is a
puzzle for me because if you have one
creature who is able to be so inventive
how is it possible that it doesn't
accumulate complexity in the technology
so the same cognitive machineries so to
speak should be able to produce more
complex artifacts so there is no kind of
accumulation of complexity across
Generations
and that's a big puzzle for me so I
thought maybe the free energy principle
was useful here too so I just made this
analogy so it's Michael who opened up
this new Avenue thanks to the work of of
Carl and I just took advantage to seeing
maybe it is because new things are too
surprising for Great Waves so there are
creatures that cannot cope with
high levels of surprise
and I mean if I'm talking too farther to
Manchester me I think you are following
the argument I assume
is it okay
so the idea is that
if something that I observe is too
surprising I have to deal with this high
level of surprise
and
also by reading a paper by Andy Clark
was the title was politic coding it was
in behave a behavior and brain Sciences
if I remember correctly he thought of
one can see very surprising things
if he's able to credit the sensual
information as opposed to the top down
prediction
and this again helped me to make the
connection so maybe the problem is that
from the point of view of the server of
an innovation
if something is too surprising I have to
consider if I trust the central
information as opposed to the the
top-down prediction and this kind of I
need to decide I mean I'm talking I need
to decide like it was some kind of
animistic thing but you know what I mean
so this is the Wake waiting up of
central information
and a top-down prediction so my idea was
that perhaps what happens here is that
this great apes when they observe
something new
and it's surprising they kind of do not
credit it so it's like they basically do
not register that because it's
um kind of is a mismatch with the
prediction and for some reason they are
not able to credit the essential
information and this brings us to the
concept of the songs of Bandit surprises
so this song is a an imaginary concept
it's something we we used to explain
what happened so it's like
if you have a wide zone of a boundary
surprisingly means that things that are
not in accordance with your top-down
predictions
things that deviate much from these two
of them predictions can be
can be handled because you are able to
bounce your prices so you have cognitive
mechanisms that help you to bounce your
presence even when you are facing huge
mismatches
uh uh with regard to your expectations
to previous expectations
so that's we
the main thing here so we propose that
in Gray devs there has not been these
changes in the brand that allow them to
bounce surprises well things deviate
marketing from when the what they expect
only indeed when they deviate the
slightly from what they expect so they
can
accumulate complexity provided the
things and they observe that are new are
not
um
very different from what they expected
and I think I will stop here and I can
make more Precision but that is the
basic idea I don't know if Michael is in
agreement or he wants to accept him
because I hope I have my limitation with
language too so perhaps you can help me
out
Michael do you have something to add or
to precise
um not really
fundamentally I
accept what Hector is saying
his idea
was certainly novel to me when he put it
forward that we have to think about The
Observers not merely the practitioners
because anthropologists and
archaeologists and indeed many people
working in the cognitive and
psychological Sciences have tended to
put the emphasis uh in terms of skills
on the person who performs them and not
the person who or not the observation of
those skills which is so necessary of
course and I didn't realize this until
Hector pointed it out to me so necessary
of course for their transmission to take
hold at all and this struck me as being
most important Insight uh so obvious
that when wonders why one never thought
of it oneself in the same way
that one wonders why it is but so many
failure anthropologists and
archaeologists uh are more concerned
with the stuff than with why the stuff
isn't there
um these are such obvious problems they
go back to Sherlock Holmes and so Arthur
Conan Doyle
um but we tend to be obsessed with what
we can see and feel and touch rather
than um with uh
what sort of
process might have um led to explaining
both present cells and absences at the
same time and this is where I find the
whole notion of active inference uh so
important to tie in with uh Evolution
um
it was Professor person himself who
enthused me to go back to the lectures
that I used to attend 50 years ago when
I was an undergraduate that were given
by Nicholas timbergan at Oxford I would
steal away from the lectures of anatomy
given by someone to grow Clark to attend
those of Nicholas tinbergen and other
people and
uh I've come to realize just how
important uh lorensis and Tim Bergens
and um of Portland Fish and Von Fishers
um Daniel knows uh were and how worthy
they were of getting 50 years ago the
Nobel Prize the physiology or medicine
um 50 years later we're still trying to
get to terms with the significance of
their insights which shows just how how
difficult it is for us to absorb novelty
but nevertheless
um uh I'm no giant I'm a dwarf uh we
stand on the shoulders of giants not
only Lawrence and tinbergen and fish
Darwin of course and um going back to
base in the 18th century one critic of
our
sciatric paper said that we were
that we were
um promo in other words we were
post-modernist no no we go back in a
good scientific and purple tradition and
theoretical tradition back to the 18th
century nothing postmodern about us at
all I think all of us would reject any
suspicion that we were involved in
post-processual and post-modernist
arguments unlike many of our uh
colleagues in what I call the Social
Studies I like the late Lou Binford and
archaeologists in America and some note
uh
I prefer social studies to social
science which I think can at times is
something of an oxymoron
um yeah I suspect that um others will
dispute that with me however
um I'm no do I'm no giant I'm a dwarf it
took me all my time to cope with
something we were never taught at school
Matrix algebra which I had to learn when
I was doing my research on
um previous skulls and
from then to cope with bass film and the
approaches or the uses that can be made
of Base mathematical statistics using
um using Matrix Theory
which I've gradually caught up with and
I can follow it but I certainly wouldn't
be capable unlike Professor Christen of
yeah of deriving it but I can certainly
understand the significance of something
that I think a lot of our colleagues in
the humanities and social studies
simply are not prepared to confront at
all
I think they prefer much more subjective
if you like post-modernist
thinking to rational scientific analysis
well thank you
what's the screen huh can you see me I
can see you I can see oh we we see you
Carl to um
well actually I just no longer quite as
good as it used to be uh
so I sometimes send your huddle over the
computer
it's all good it's all good Carl maybe
you could come in and um share how this
collaboration came to be or from your
view from the inside or however else
you'd like to comment on what we've seen
so far
yes well thank you very much for the
opportunity
um I I I also have to do a lot of
huddling because of my failing eyesight
um so yeah just to reiterate your what a
joy was to hear that presentation and
Hector's follow-up um so this is this is
uh for me an adventure well outside my
comfort zone so I'm here as a passenger
and spectator
um and learning a lot I I didn't know
half of this stuff
um uh you know even though I did a lot
of uh biology and a little bit of
evolutionary um biology as a young man
but this is this is intriguing and
um foundational insights into the way
that we are
um so I'm I'm gonna make a few comments
it's gonna be more of a stream of
Consciousness but I qualify this again
but this is this is completely outside
my comfort zone I'm just talking as a
layperson here or a lay physicist
perhaps
um and I'll just make a few observations
but I mean I've been particularly
interested in your synthesis because of
course you have a probably more than any
of us the broader oversight from The
evolutionary perspective right through
to the the Bayesian mechanics that um is
entailed by things like active inference
so
um I I just to forewarn you I'm going to
call upon you to to do this do the
synthesis and to draw and and join the
dots that haven't already been joined
although there's been a lot of dot
joining um from what I can see already
um
so the stream of Consciousness
comes really from
um this
um commitment to ideas that are
certainly not postmodern I think I'd
probably have to go back to Plato
um and certainly sort of uh get stuck
around the the ear of helmholtz and the
like uh you know from from the um from
the physicists uh point of view
um and assuming that looking at the
looking at the this sort of remarkable
uh Snakes and Ladders phenomenon from
Through The Eyes of a physicist and it
certainly makes
um complete sense that if we're looking
at a uh a process that would be
described as a non-equilibrium steady
state that is slowly evolving
um
that could be if you like a mathematical
image of The evolutionary process the
definitive feature of these
non-equilibrium steady States
that have
um um
the your biological aspect is that they
entail a revisiting of the trajectory to
neighborhoods of certain parts of face
space so if I read face spaces basically
the state of evolution or what what
phenotypes are doing or what is encoded
genetically in a very very crude broad
level
there can be no other solution to a
particular trajectory that is up for
describing a non-equilibrium steady
state than the occasional ion Tyrant
recurrence of certain states of being
literally being close
um or revisiting neighborhoods of uh
certain
um regimes of Faith space
um so
the snakes and ladders
um image seems to me a very apt image to
actually describe all back attractors
which are another way of articulating
these kinds of Dynamics or this kind of
kind of Dynamics in the sense that they
have this aspect of recurrence and they
have this aspect of self-contained
itinerancy which are the Hallmarks of
any system really that exists over a
substantial period of time
um only you know it would be interesting
to think can it be any other way and I
would submit no you know if you have
um a a physical process this is
unfolding at multiple time scales and
and it is endowed and can be recognized
either historically or in the Moment by
by being in certain characteristic
States and literally uh characterize the
system in question so that it can be
named
um you know whether it's a species or
whether it's your behavior or whether
it's an artifact or whether it's a
process
um then it must be the case that it has
this uh it has this kind of iteriency
where things come and go so it will be
interesting just to um if you're in a um
as a pure exercise for pure mathematics
to support things like the ponkare
recurrence theorem into a snakes on
ladders format
um and vice versa because I think
there's something fundamentally true it
has to be that has to be the way that
things are
um and I I see that
um in many fields
um
the
um and two immediately came to mind
um the first was
um current Notions of the not the spread
of ideas or the spread of tools but the
spread of cancer you know the view that
cancer
um there are two views of cancer there's
a sort of 20th century view that you get
a one cell in your body
fails to recognize that it should not be
growing and just keeps on growing and
you'll get these uh
um Progressive and inevitable growth of
the cancer
um set of cells and at some point they
will disseminate and see themselves
around the body you get in this past the
season second risk and the like and
ultimately unless it's cured then it
will it will destroy the phenotype
there's another view which is is now
becoming more prevalent which is a much
more Snakes and Ladders View and this
view is that
um where all the time generating little
cancer cells but 99.9 of the of the time
they don't get a foothold
so that we're in the equilibrium
um or hopefully on the right side of an
equilibrium always being host to little
cancer cells uh it's just that it's very
rarely that they actually establish
themselves to us to the extent that they
can um get a foothold and reproduced to
actually produce a you know a tumor
um or a neoplastic growth and and that
that struck me it would be nice to put a
snakes and ladders sort of picture on uh
the way that that particular biological
natural system
um
is viewed and it's certainly very
consistent with current views on cancer
the other thing
um the other system
um that seems to comply with this notion
is not again the spread of ideas or the
spread of uh tools or cultural means
um that the spread of viruses in
epidemiology you know it's very
interesting that
um that there are certain
um viruses for example that get a
foothold and explode exponentially and
we've had you know we've just enjoyed or
witnessed a um an episode of that with
the with the uh the recent covid-19
pandemic but there are other
um very very similar episodes that don't
get a foothold and they they they die
out very very quickly because they can't
spread
um and um I I know this personally
because we were looking for data when
modeling using actually exactly the same
maths that underwrites the engine
principle active influence we were
modeling the coronavirus crisis recently
and we hope to get some priors on
certain parameters by looking at Legacy
historical data that and it's
interesting that there is data out there
on very similar viral epidemics but they
died out too quickly to generate enough
data to make sense of
um so things like MERS for example
um was so recorded but it went away
before it actually produced enough data
to get a handle on it
um so again
um you know this phenomena of
um sort of things repeating themselves
you know you know climbing up the ladder
but then sometimes uh falling down a
stake very very quickly so that they you
have to wait until the next occurrence
seems to be a fundamental uh fundamental
um aspect of
um
Ensemble Dynamics wherever you see it
either within the body in terms of near
play Zero um in terms of epidemiology
and sped and I use the word spread
deliberately because of the you know
that that latter perspective on
um basically to copy or not to copy so
if if you're copying then you um then
you're in the game of spelling
um and if you don't copy then you don't
spend so I think just coming back to you
know
um to the question
um
you know what what what is it that
determines whether a particular
cognitive supplies a your a novel
um approach to uh you know a way of
Behaving or indeed a way of being
catches on or not
um and um you know that dialectic I
think is you know it's absolutely
intriguing I should just say the course
all of this formulation rests very very
sensitively on a separated temporal
scales you know and
um
you know we have to sort of be in the
background there is always this
um
separation of scales that you get with
with Evolution
um
and in this particular instance what we
are talking about is really whether
um certain things can survive
generationally
um in the spirit I would imagine of sort
of Evo Devo and cultural Niche
construction
um and then the question then is okay at
a fast time scale of
your interactions between phenotypes and
what's going to make that sufficiently
endemic to be
um propagated at a transgenerational uh
time scale
um I think that's a really interesting
question
um you know against the kind of question
which uh
um as a neuroscientist and same as a
clinician you are often um confronted
with your things for example like
um epilepsy you know what is it that um
constraint that determines whether a
particular epileptic surprising Dynamic
discharge in a particular part of the
brain
can be propagated and disseminated
throughout the brain to give you a fit
or as opposed to it sort of Auto
vituating or you know quenching itself
because the neighboring cells are just
not interested they just don't recognize
that particular pattern and it's um and
and it's and it's inhibited
um and I guess the answer I mean I think
we've already had the answer
um both Michael and Hector have
articulated it but
um the I guess the answer lies in the
mechanics of the spread of ideas and
shared frames of reference and whether
it is too surprising
um to be incorporated into your con
specifics or your your community
um or whether it is learnable
um and can be
um incorporated or absorbed into your
generative models
um such that it can then be spread to
the next person you know in in the
standard sense of sort of um Niche
construction
um and Hector mentioned specifically one
key determinant of that which is the um
of Robertson's Michael but it was the
the ability to
um change your mind
um and you know the ability to change
your mind is absolutely fundamental and
if you just you know if you want to
frame this in an active inference
context
um just confronted with a cognitive
surprisal as it has been articulated a
set of difficult to explain
um Sensations or sensory evidence then
there are two ways in which you can
resolve that surprise the first way is
to change your mind and to adjust your
internal generative models or your do
some amazing beliefs updating on the
inside to make sense of this thing and
that might
depend upon some experience dependent
learning over a suitable time scale
um so that you're changing your model
your generative model of the world to
make it more apt to explain this novel
observational or observation of one of
your con specifics doing this kind of
thing them the other thing the other way
is not the
um the perceptual response the belief
updating on the inside to make your
predictions more like the sensations
it's to actually act upon the world to
um to make your Sensations more like
they were predicted so this is a fun
this is foundational inactive influence
and there's two complementary ways of
minimizing surprise or or prediction
error you either change your mind or you
change the thing that you're surprised
about
um you know at every level at every
temporal scale so just read in terms of
whether I um
I'm able to change my mind about
witnessing fire there are two ways I can
say yes fire is a thing and you know I
can then
um incorporate or imbibe that into my
world and model
um
um become the kind of creature that
actually engages with fire or I can act
to put the fire out and then I don't
have to worry about it both are
perfectly appropriate ways of minimizing
surprise and the difference
at a very basic level
um the um the thing that determines what
I um whether I uh perceive or act or
whether I engage in perceptual or active
inference
um in the moment to moment depends
exactly on something which was
um again mentioned implicitly earlier on
which is the Precision afforded your the
sensory evidence relative to your prior
beliefs so as a physiologist
um if you don't know this you know it
was a beautiful there were beautiful
illustrations of this so if we if you if
we just forget about the notion um at
the moment of sort of long-term
revisions or belief updating of our
generative model over multiple
experiences to an instance of somebody
making a fire
um or providing me with a Valentine's
gift of a hand ax
um and just get the thing now to um the
moment-to-moment ways of making uh of
sampling the world and making sense of
the world
um it's the case that in order to move
in order to change the world
I have to attenuate the Precision
afforded my sensory information because
if I didn't do that
I would not be able to ignore all the
evidence that I'm not currently moving
so the most beautiful example of this I
think is something called circadic
suppression
it's when we move our eyes and we do so
about four times a second
we actually attenuate the Precision of
the sensory evidence
uh so that we are able to actually move
our eyes which basically means you can't
see the optic flow induced when you make
a sharp or psychatic eye movement and
yet 50 milliseconds after you've made
the eye movement you're suddenly now
attending to the visual information that
you can see so you can't you can't
actually see anything while your eyes
are moving because you've got this
sensory attenuation
which is basically putting the priors
um you're in charge uh suspending
attention to the sensorium while you are
acting
um failures of that
um and have quite horrible consequences
so a failure to ignore the evidence that
I'm not moving and the failure to
attenuate or suspend attention attenuate
the Precision of sensory evidence or
afforded sensory evidence
um looks think like things like
Parkinson's disease so you know we think
that
um this Precision is encoded by certain
neurochemical Transmissions particularly
dopamine a deficit of dopamine basically
means an inability to
um attenuate the evidence from your
um stress receptors or all these signals
coming from the body and that you're not
currently moving so if you have the
probably believe I'm going to move I'm
going to sit up walk
um drink from this cup you may have that
primarily but it's immediately
counteracted by and dispelled by very
precise evidence you're not moving so
you can never actually initiate a
movement and what you actually see
clinically is basically a psychomota
poverty or or a bradykinesia the point
I'm making here all reduces to something
very very simple which is the Precision
afforded sensory evidence and if you
can't get that right and notice it has
to be estimated at every time scale
either in terms of psychotic suppression
on a a 10 millisecond time scale right
through to um
that one might actually argue
um
an evolutionary time scale and I make
that argument because
um precision
is it it can also be thought of as a
rate constant so if if I've got some
sort of um sensory evidence and some
prior beliefs
um and I now view my belief updating at
any level whether it's sort of you know
my neural activity encoding my beliefs
at the moment or whether it's my
um my neuronal connectivity or
um you know encoding what I have learned
or what's neurodevelopment or indeed out
of the evolutionary time scale the
Precision can be read as a rate constant
so now what we're talking about is a
certain quantity that is absolutely
crucial for whether I um adopt this
um or incorporate
um instill this novel experience into my
model or not that depends upon a
Precision or a rate constant which means
that
um one would um if one wanted to ask the
question you know why do some species
have the ability to
um
to learn uh whereas other species don't
then I think the the answer is quite
simply in their ability to um to
optimize and adjust their learning rate
either Precision afforded the evidence
at hand that drives the learning
um and I I'm wondering whether there are
a couple of ways to take that that sort
of
um mathematical take on this on this
really single really important quantity
team and just to make it intuitive I'm
trying to get back to the copy versus
not copy so if I can copy that means
that I am um I'm impressed
impressionable what does that mean it
means that I will accumulate new
evidence very very quickly what does
that mean that means I have the capacity
to assign greater evidence to or
Precision to that sensory evidence and
suspend the Precision of my prior
beliefs I'm not rigid in my thinking I
can learn because I am impressionable
um what would that look like what would
look like you were young it would look
like you have just been born and you are
designed to learn because you you have
yet to build neurodevelopmentally your
model of the world
um which means that
um averaged over a lifetime the um the
degree to which you are likely to learn
and implicitly enable the spread of
ideas
um and you know ignite this particular
lab episode of
um your of a new tool or a new a new way
of doing things or
um being
um then it would look as if you are
younger for longer so I'm just I was
just intrigued I think I think Michael I
was making a explicit reference to the
fact that
um that
it may be some there may be a key
difference between certain species maybe
the um the duration or the timing of the
point where you basically switch off
your learnability you switch off your uh
impression ability and you become an
adult and you bake in then and then from
that point on you become old and wise
and stuck in your ways and instead of
actually trying to change your mind when
something changes you don't you become
non-conservative in a political sense
but you actually uh try to keep things
status quo commit to the social norms
but before that you don't you explore
you go to discos you do bungee jumping
you
um you know make new friends but if it's
the case then that the the the spread of
ideas depends upon being a child at
heart for longer then then
that observation about at what point do
we
um get to that uh epigenetically
determined stage of neurodevelopment
becomes absolutely crucial I'm just even
longer this is the final Point
um
an even longer time scale I'm wondering
whether the same maths can be borrowed
or the same Concepts at least can be
borrowed
um to think about
um this kind of evolvability on the
perspective of people like Stuart
Kaufman and like so selection for
selectability so again if you're now
reading these rate constants or
precisions
um uh in an evolutionary setting what
you're what you are talking about is
basically the the you know the mutation
rates or the selectability
um which of course itself can be subject
to selective pressure
so you know if you
um if you commit to this style of
thinking about belief updating in a in a
in a mathematical sense at many
different levels or different spatial
temporal scales on these temporal scales
um then it may be that the the selection
for selectability or the selectability
in and of itself is
um exactly the same kind of quantity
that is the your the learnability and
the be you know being young at heart for
longer that just is the same kind of um
quantity that is uh required right down
to the level of uh psychotic suppression
and sensory tenuation that determines
when we act to keep the world constant
as opposed to no we actually have to
attend to this evidence and and update
our beliefs
um and um
if that's the case then
um this notion uh well I just wanted to
to close on on on sort of the importance
of um cultural Niche construction
um looked at
um through the lens of these this
um rate of
um adaptation Precision selectability at
different levels and how all of these
couple to each other in a sort of
bootstrapping way and whether that would
be you're a useful view of
um the spread of the spread of ideas
um sometimes spelling and sometimes not
spreading
um can I just ask it that
did we um did we or did did you
laterally
um
sort of Leverage
um sort of the well actually though this
is basically setting up Daniel for his
his perspective but I'm just wondering
how much
um people in um Evo Devo and uh
evolution is psychology I'm thinking
here people like Cecilia Hayes and uh
cognitive gadgets how much they they
think about these um these issues and
whether there's the opportunity or
whether they have a snakes and ladders
like
um view of things uh from the point of
view of
um evolutionary psychology
and that's it that's all I have to say
thank you Daniel
your turd
thank you wow
barely no
which side of that hand ax to flake
um the
multi-scale learning is a great point
and perspective
we can just imagine the extreme cases
in the total
acceptance of sensory evidence world
then that thing defined by its
revisiting potentially infrequently of
characteristic states that thing ceases
to be that thing in that whether that's
seen in some positive
um light a neutral entanglement light or
a death like light it will cease to be
that thing because it will have just
simply informationally if not
bio-materially accepted the generative
processes in positions and then the
other extreme case would be no attention
ah See No Evil Hear No Evil
and in that case the trajectory from a
Bayesian mechanics perspective is
massive it's a a trajectory with so much
inertia that it can't be moved and that
sounds like
it would ever happen but in fact when we
heard from Hector and Michael that like
upon seeing an innovation
a gray ape does not take up that
Innovation there prior on how to
accomplish a behavioral outcome or even
at a higher order some functional
outcome
can be seen as massive the Bayesian
physical inertia of their top down prior
dominates these potentially sparse or
non-linearly related cues coming up from
the bottom so simply by not paying
attention to the bottom-up cues
there's the imposition of this top-down
mass and so that's a Bayesian mechanical
way to understand well if we had no
priors at all no prior no problem but
then we dissolve but if we have
um the Titanic prior then
it's a fragile strategy and so if the
niche were very simple and unchanging
that may be locally in adaptive strategy
and on certain axes of phenotype where
there can be regularities we do see
those kinds of strategies like a
bacterium that has selected to live in a
constant temperature geothermal niche
may come to entrench in its protein
structure and in its gene regulatory
networks and so on
in embodiments that sharpens and
sharpens and sharpens its capacity to
compete in that regularity from a
temperature perspective
and therefore at the detriment of
Fitness in changing environments
so that's one aspect is seeing learning
as this multi-scale
synergetic and ongoing renegotiation
process
of the updating across multiple scales
some spatial temporal scales of which
there are no problems with talking about
those using the cognitive ontology like
perception cognition and action
but then some scales especially Beyond
the physical mechanisms that those
cognitive ontological terms arose from
it becomes like well what does it mean
for the population to pay attention to
something or what does it mean for the
Niche to pay attention to something
so that was one angle on the rates and
it speaks to the importance of having
flexible and interoperable Mathematics
and statistics and Analysis Frameworks
so we can just qualitatively even in
conversation
start to see that as a starting point
instead of needing to argue up to that
point of that being important for
example in pursuit of transdisciplinary
synthesis conceptually epistemically or
so that we could explain predict design
control create pragmatically
how can we take that multi-scale insight
as our starting points
and then I think that leads to a
question in the chat which I will ask
now
Mark frickman wrote
early in the video was the complaint
that there was a lack of evidence as to
why certain things occurred in the
archaeological evidence record
how does active inference not suffer
from the same issue
and so it's a key question thank you
Mark for asking and was the motivation
for
one of my underlying motivations for
even reading and investigating with this
lens was
great if we can describe everything
and we have this very interesting
mathematics and so on how do we go from
a technique and a method
to
moving beyond some limitations of
previous analysis techniques
with respect especially to the
historical record
we can go to Dean
or whomever else has a thought
I can I can throw something in but I'm
not sure it's it's going to satisfy
directly the question
um maybe somebody else wants to hear
something about it
here I
indirectly answered the question and
I'll come and I'll Loop into what I
think might be satisfying
part of it
I think one of the things that that in
particular that to copy or not to copy
paper emphasizes is the observer's
perspective
so rather than just looking at that as a
as something written down on a page
taking up or absorbing that position
the observer's perspective I think what
the two papers and and one of the things
that we try to highlight in and we're so
grateful that Michael and and Carl and
and Hector were
willing to let us look at two things at
once
was the idea that the papers
um both raised the Specter of and I put
quotes around this
The Narrative follows
what the implications of start with a
story about seeing phenomena X actually
are
now one of the implications of that is
that when you have a story you can't
have gaps in the plot
so people who are are really story
biased
and story forward they want those gaps
filled in as quickly as possible that's
how we comprehend
but the interesting thing is
if we are actually actively inferring as
opposed to just seeing it as a subject
matter or a topic
we can take a game theory approach and
in games there will be random gaps like
Charles Sanders Pierce says an
exhaustive inquiry well if it's
exhaustive we're also going to need
recovery and reflection and and so on so
there will be gaps and so the snakes and
ladders metaphor to me is like okay
perfect now we're starting with a game
as opposed to the retelling or the
manufacturing of starting with a story
so there's very different mechanisms
in in the two approaches
right there are there are very different
assumptions
in the two approaches and then the
question around modeling as per as
perspective swapping
kind of pivots on
the stuff that Michael was talking about
in terms of
how is the change based model
depth capacity either affording or not
affording that ability to play with time
as opposed to being captured by it
because in a story you've
you've written down what the sequence is
it's now
been applied now you can interpret that
but in terms of that actual effort of
starting with the story it's now
stabilized per se relatively speaking so
let's start with the game
and Carl's heard this before because I
asked him a question about a year and a
half maybe two years ago is starting
with a game is a prediction matter
expertise strategy or a bias
starting with a story is a subject
matter expertise strategy or a bias
and you can understand why if you're if
you're dealing with historical records
to fall into a default of okay well we
have to start with the story
but I think what Hector and Michael are
are at least asking us to have a
conversation around is
well so what if we do bring this other
way of viewing
the circumstances taking that game
strategy and putting it on the same
Shelf
as the story strategy
so again if you if you look at the
assumptions around why gaps have to be
filled in as opposed to there will be
gaps because the game is on
something as simple as that and being
able to hold the two things up at once
can sometimes
at least tell you a little bit about
maybe some of the
some of these conditions that you as the
Observer are inserting on what it is
that you're observing or examining
was it Sherlock who said the game is
afoot
Maybe
right
yeah
okay yes Carl
indeed uh Michael or Hector
how is this Landing with with what
you're thinking right now
Michael go ahead
you always know better
then I can pick up from you
I'm not quite sure where to begin
um
perhaps
thinking in terms of the
evolution of
both the brain and the body in the
Guinness homo
uh
we
and possibly neanderthals also
maybe from as early as three quarters of
a million or even or at least half a
million years ago
seem to have undergone
an evolution towards a bimodal growth
spurt or growth curve now caused by the
Adolescent growth spurt following a
period period of childhood slowing down
in growth which is unique in our ganus
to organize
and
seems to be related in adolescence to
some changes in terms of the agility
to react to a complex situations or not
as the case may be
but even before that in early childhood
I'm now talking about the first three or
four years of life our infants seemed to
have exceeded already quite considerably
their cognitive ability particularly
with regard to working memory when
contrasted against the present great
apes
in other words there has definitely been
not merely an expansion of the brain
but in particular
changes in
the connective systems within the brain
which clearly must have an evolutionary
physical basis in terms of uh structure
both
endure and in particular in draw
neuronal structure which when I began to
study medicine physiology over a long
time ago now 1960
um we could barely imagine
uh
it was only in the very end of the 1950s
I think 59 if I'm not mistaken a very
sufficient can correct me that at
Cambridge Henry huxler was doing uh and
uh began to do intra neural studies on
on action potentials we were doing them
in the lab at Oxford as undergraduates
about four years later and then I was
doing them under Professor power Gleason
a few years later still with a practical
application
um because we were studying uh the
change the changes in these following
orthocracial phosphate poisoning which
had a structural situation in hens which
we were working on similar to those in
humans who had suffered from a massive
outbreak of poisoning at agadir in
Morocco when
a lot of local people were sold American
jet fuel oil rich in autocracial
phosphates for cooking with and there
was an epidemic and many deaths which
was well known in in medical history and
so some of these early studies even then
were having applications which now seem
almost Paleolithic when we think of the
work which is being done on Antonio
Illinois and also on synaptic
connectivity
neuronal transmission and the effects
not merely
of genetics such as for example synaptic
pruning but also of epigenetic
modifications which no doubt
we shall learn a lot more about in the
coming decades but which even now seem
to be telling us that the increase in
um the kind of connectivity or
um what's the word I'm really looking
for that's connectivity is not the best
word within the brain
much more greater than anything which is
possible within even growing chimpanzees
let alone the adults or other great apes
and this must have evolved somehow uh
probably in relation to the appearance I
suspect of the slowing down of childhood
growth followed by the uniquely human
homo adolescent growth spurt which was
completely absent one and a half million
years ago in early Homo erectus
according to
um
Professor Christopher Dean and others
and which must surely have been a
response for The evolutionary change
must have been a response to not merely
no merely some kind of magical
physiological change but more more
likely to
the effects of
what we might call Behavioral responses
and fundamentally it takes us back to
active influence and to
fundamental changes which are naturally
slow uh to evolve and this is the part
which is not recognized by most of our
colleagues who work with living
organisms on living primates and to that
matter living human communities and
individuals
their perspective is not that
I hope they'll forgive me for saying
this
which those of us who've been brought up
in the Natural Sciences naturally come
to expect they don't have the kind of
cosmic
time scale of cosmic spatial scale of
things
and of their the slowness and the
imperceptibility of change
which come naturally to those of us
brought up from school days in a
different tradition
and I think this is very important
because I think there is a big divide
still between
what um six years ago we knew as being
named the two cultures I think this
divide still exists
um as that critic of our paper claimed
we were post-modernists uh clearly
represents
um the more uh shall we say
um
intuitive
relativistic view in which there is
something which some of them believe to
want to call an ethnographical Pleasant
which I think is is a contradiction in
terms otherwise it would be it could
have been no evolution in Behavior but
which wants to compare uh instead of
contrast as I would have it uh what goes
on in a few Generations let's say in a
community computer smaller I don't know
about a large one today with what went
on over many many generations
um as I said between 2 million and 200
000 years ago there would have been at
least 80 000 Generations if each was 25
years long and even that is pushing it a
bit given that adulthood in home of the
actors was very likely achieved before
the age of 15 and reproductive success
was probably the next generation was
probably
um only a few years away
this is important because as Professor
Christian remote talking about cancer
um our longevity
um
has allowed us to and of course I'm a
better hygiene and medical knowledge but
particularly our longevity has permitted
us to
survive in ways that were Unthinkable
perhaps
um in many parts of the world uh valid
um well less than 100 years ago
that wasn't merely thanks to antibiotics
or even better hygiene
in but
to increases in standard of living going
back perhaps perhaps um a few hundred
years but let's not get into that what I
really want to say is that
next week I have to have a small
vessel cell neoplasm removed from the
side of my nose which only at the age of
80 or 81 became uh noticeable
indicating that some of these
um
diseases which we we know the God is
being a part and parcel of our Humanity
or the aortic stenosis which was I was
diagnosed with with my first and only
ever incident of of um
of um um
cardiac failure
about a year ago and has been
successfully treated thanks though uh uh
modern catheterization uh versus versus
allow profitable prostheties to be but
of the Prosthetics of uh to be placed on
heart valves by a long catheter from the
groin this kind of thing would have been
Unthinkable
um a few years ago in fact I can
remember as an undergraduate
um
medical student watching the first ever
open heart operations done by Alf
gunning which was regarded in 1960
whether it was 63 64 as being something
that might never might never succeed and
nowadays is operations on our heart is
just regarded as everyday cancers in
cardiovascular units around the world
things are changing and they're changing
it
within acceleration which we can only
barely appreciate there are even those
of us who now outlived our Portugal
years and 10 and are on the verge of uh
of defunct dysfunction
however
um we have to think in terms of the and
this again is important of the
exponential uh if you like or the crude
leg scale at which
things are happening and which are so
influencing many people many of our
colleagues in the
humanities and in the social studies and
indeed studies of animal behavior
um
including climate behavior of course
and this I think is detracting from an
appreciation of the long time scale and
the
um over which evolutionary processes
have uh necessarily do take place I
don't believe in Welch Smith's
um
hopeful monsters magical genes some
people believe that there's a magical
Gene in Homo sapiens switched on our
cognitive ability I think this is this
is wishful thinking
um indeed it's magical thinking in my
view however
um I suppose
uh my own training would lead me to want
to say that but I'm not there have been
exceptions and one exception I should
like to mention by name is an Emeritus
Buffet
mythology was eminent uh in Paleolithic
studies of York University now Professor
Jeff Bailey who over 40 years ago was
pointing out the incremental ability of
the time scales of recent archeology and
if you like ethnography with those of
the Paleolithic and the pleistocene and
human evolution and this was not really
well regarded at the time although it
influenced me very greatly and um
so there have been honorable exceptions
um who certainly um influenced me
um
we do as I say stand on the shoulders of
others we try to
um make one of your
small
conference advances in birth methodology
and in theoretical
influences and deductions and I think
that they
uh
we're finally coming to possibly begin
to see how to bring together
thanks to
um especially Professor friston's
insights and
um methodological
um
what I'm trying to say
methodological proposals and advances we
need to see that it might be possible to
square the circle to bring together the
evolutionary
very slow
evolutionary development of the
hierarchical
um
mind which characterizes our Guinness
and
actual
processes which
can underpin this undergird it
can bring together the
no I went in view which
um most of us at the spouse in the west
uh with a few exceptions which are too
well known to be worth mentioning here
um I'm sure Daniel knows more about them
than I do
um
but um
it's meaning to bring together uh
the
CRV of the evolution of species by
natural selection of and within species
and are Within part is important and
it's beginning to bring it to together
with what we can appreciate about human
behavior which is so
different from that of the right age and
here I just like to make one final point
which is that
in another paper which we
um which Hector and our co-authors along
with
um and Professor might read of UCLA
um in
um
we pointed out that there has been too
much in our view uh hopeful or wishful
thinking about the human nature of great
apes certainly their behavior is very uh
different from that of
um
many other orders of mammals and
not to mention uh other failure uh other
um classes within the animal kingdom
however
there is a big difference and I think
this difference uh is best
um emphasized by going back to the
growth curve of humans
and of human behavior in relation to our
childhood in particular our infants are
capable by about the age of three of
putting of combination combinatorial uh
thinking in ways that are virtually
impossible or outside the scope of the
behavior of most
um
gray tapes most of the time and almost
certainly in the wild and this I think
uh demands an explanation which is more
than simply saying no the apes are
really more like us it's just that we
don't recognize this no I think that
there is a difference and the time scale
uh has to be taken into consideration
which it often is not and most
importantly this brings it move back to
my last point and the first one which is
that finally we're beginning to get
together thanks to Professor Christensen
Kristen's insights to seeing the
possibility of tying together
the biological evolution and if you like
um the psychological Evolution certainly
I would say the neurobiological
evolution
which has characterized our Guinness and
characterizes it today in a unique way
and with that no that's my case
thank you Michael
many many ways to go
the dinner plate balanced on top of the
stick
and I think that's the cognitive moment
where the top-down constraints and
opportunities
of our enabling architectures
which for a long time included primarily
what was on board
and then over the last several thousand
years
progressively included Niche
modifications and stigmergic
modifications like writing
and so just like in the SPM toolkit for
studying brain function there are brain
regions that have statistical
connections that aren't necessarily
anatomically connected and vice versa
and
when we consider information spaces
we have similar connectivity patterns
some are like information anatomy and
some are more like information
physiology
in narrative or rhetorical spaces
that becomes part of our extended
cognitive
selves
and
leave to others
in the best possible way those who want
bright lines of what is a self
there are analytic Frameworks that
respect continuities and discontinuities
with an emphasis on the respect
the continuities we want them to be
differentiable and integrated and
generalized coordinates of motion and
the continuous time active inference
models and the path integral formulation
and then the discrete time generative
model
which is also a map not the territory
helps us understand saltatory
Maneuvers over multiple time scales and
looking back at the literature and the
discourse
discussions like
well is evolution gradual or general
uh and jumping
these have been some of the biggest
touch points
are things slowly changing or fast
changing
those are
where certain lines were drawn
and
the methodological
developments
Bayesian graphs and
so on and so on
have provided a
instrumentalist lens
that as a matter of fact does integrate
these Frameworks methodologically
that is a claim that hardly anyone
dissents from
and then what happens
with respect to our past present and
future
when we realize that we're after the
moments of intra and among disciplinary
tension
not pushing the the rock up the hill
anymore
or trying to bring somebody else along
but
gardening in a space that already is how
we need it to be
could I make a comment uh Daniel yeah
just occurred to me
that
when we think of the formant frequencies
that affect all of the harmonics and
other aspects of our vocalizations
whether speech chanting song or even
whistling perhaps
it is unlikely or improbable that
these very many variants which occur in
different languages throughout the world
with they're very very different
characteristics
and which former certainly began had
begun to evolve quite considerably by
the time that early writing appears
about five thousand years ago
but it's still unlikely that these can
be
taken back into the past on a slow
evolving time scale such that
they can be related directly in a direct
evolutionary line to the vocalizations
as I say of great apes from a common
ancestor that we have with them six
million years ago
if we accept this uh unlikelhood
then it seems equally unlikely to me
that we can talk about cultural
transmission or technological
transmission
in a slow uh
um
uh uniform manner
invariant manner over the past let's say
two million years from which we have
information about different technical
skills and Technical abilities uh or at
least
um so we say
technical possibilities that were
exploited by our organist or no
and
therefore
I would argue that
it is equally likely that the
unawareness of what people what
individuals will actually enacting the
unawareness by bystanders onlookers or
even their very protagonist uh
protagonists of those activities
themselves
uh was a continuous and continuous
Evolution over let us say 80 or at least
60 000 Generations in a continuous
invariant manner this seems unlikely and
it seems equally unlikely that
the same is true of different uh
linguistic
shall we say
abilities
or aptitudes in other words as Professor
for instance was remarked in more than
one paper
it does seem that
the advantages that were taken uh
were taken
not on a continuous manner but in a
discontinuous manner when particular
communicative skills
had developed in some groups such as to
be able to widen their social scope for
active influence and ahead of all by an
actual selection within a shared
framework of adaptive prior beliefs
favoring alignment of common expected
expectations and Joint activities
affecting their ecological niche
formation or development and this it
seems to me is
a a very expedient way of looking at how
things happened or likely to have
happened whether we will ever be able to
produce
um a theoretic in terms of
formal version proposal for this I don't
know I would like to think so but I
really don't know how I don't have the
competence to begin to do this myself
um but I think that it is
it will if it is possible it will
certainly
be to put it mildly a challenge
to those who tend to think that there is
a rapid jump uh well rapid jump took
place uh which shall we say a small Gap
there's only a small Gap that separates
us from the great apes of the
um of the equatorial latitudes of the
old world
I think that that
took a lot much longer period of time
and I don't think that one could I don't
think that uh to compel what modern even
shall we say in inverted Commerce
relatively simple or primitive
communities uh do or how they act is
commensurable
with the behavior of modern great apes
frankly I would uh I would like to
challenge this and I would hope that it
might be possible to produce a model
which will permit the theoretic which
will permit
The evolutionary process to believe at
least
interpreted in an alternative fashion
so I didn't mean to be long-winded I
apologize
the classical information is inscribed
on the holograph
in the classical sedimentary layers is
muted
sorry in the in the holograph we have
the inscription of the classical
information
and the quantum cognitive moment is the
unpacking or the rotation of what is on
the holograph into the information space
and that I think was provocatively
raised when you asked what if
this was all there ever was
what if there wasn't a secondhand ax to
find out that field site
that's the interpretive moment
and
how
we interpret it is everything
so in our final 10 minutes of this
continuous
53.1
if each of us could provide a kind of
closing
just several minutes or any several
thoughts
on anything they'd like to add into this
session or any directions that they
would like to seed or prompt for next
week's 53.2
I have something Daniel that would like
to contribute before we we close the
session uh I would like to take
advantage the professor please donate
with us because I have some
um questions for him that had to do with
the priority principle and to copy and
not to copy if you allow me to just
formulate it and first thing I would
like to do is that there were some
losses in my argumentation before I want
to make clear that chimpanzees and learn
socially this is something we know for
sure so there is social learning
and there is even cultures as Professor
Andre Witten in in San Andreas proven
such as demonstrated so there are some
cultural tradition what is lacking is uh
accumulation of complexity what is
called by Michael tomasello ratcheting
up okay so from one generation to the
next every generation builds upon what
was produced in last generation so you
have a tool Implement and you modify it
you make it more complex so our
technology is the result of many people
accumulating their knowledge so it's
kind of a joint Endeavor this I wanted
to make clear and what the models
propose theoretical and and other kind
of models is that copying with Fidelity
is key to have this acceleration of
complexity
so what I wanted to correct is that
the puzzle is that High rates I mean
innovativeness does not realize in an
accretation of complex technology
because there is a lack of coping with
fidelity what is called true imitation
for some and for Jerusalem and ambition
they call it impersonation so I see
someone doing something I copy the the
means and the result so chimpanzees are
more prompted or likely to to emulate
which is copying the end result but by
their own devices so they can do
different things to produce the same
result and it appears that coping with
Fidelity is is key and I'm I'm I'm
cutting this a long explanation I just
wanted to correct this for the sake of
of purity of Science and now my question
for Professor Crystal if you allow me
um
there is something interesting that the
team of Andrew Witten in in San Andreas
observed and that is in our paper that
there was one instance that I know of
when there was this kind of accumulation
of complexity in chimpanzes and the
thing was possible because these
chimpanzees that combine two different
techniques to make something more
complex we could be a kind of premi
Genius example of what we call this a
creation of ratcheting up or behavior
they did it because they had
performed or enacted these behaviors
before and this is for me it's very
intriguing because thinking of how
um
in 2010 there is this paper by priests
and another people where they they talk
of the generative models under the
furniture principle and they talk of an
active inference like genetic model or
not the structural representation is
nothing that you enact you entail with
your whole body so to speak accordingly
wisdom so I'm thinking that this guy
this team punches that they were able to
have these complex a tool product
they had enacted the behaviors
independently before so by wondering if
this enacting the behavior before allow
them to overcome surprising because this
would be we go to the core of this idea
of an active inference like if you have
performed those things separately with
your body then the surprise is
kind of bounded and you can
produce this more complex product I mean
I I don't know if that was clear enough
but this is something that is intriguing
to me and
sure Carl as your as your last thought
feel free to address that or anything
else
then well yes I'm just reflecting on on
that um I think very important question
I mean it is certainly the case that all
of the um the active inference formalism
um both in Neuroscience but also in
terms of you know Ensemble Dynamics and
self-organization of collections of um
things
um rests upon
um
a generative model of the consequences
of my action
um even to the extent You could argue uh
from a theological perspective that all
our perception is just in service of
deciding what's the best thing to do
next and literally how to move next uh
just acknowledging that only a very
limited number of ways you can actually
change the universe you can either move
a striated muscle
or you can secrete something there's not
much else you can do and so
um you know it becomes very important in
terms of
um
your characteristic state of being and
to have the right generative models that
choose the right ways to move your
muscles or to speak things
um and that places embodied action or
having
um
embodimented in activism at the center
of the generative models and it
certainly makes sense to me from the
point of view of um
but the statistician and
um a machine learning Enthusiast that it
would be
um it would be much easier to revise or
update a generative model in the sense
you were intonating in terms of
um accommodating the next kind of
behavior
um you know I'm not sure what this is
composing a sequence of behaviors but
certainly being able to incrementally
um embellish
um uh or adopt a behavior if you had
already a precursor that was inherent in
the structure or could be scaffolded
within your genitive model so I mean the
idea here is that everything that goes
on the outside has to be in some
structural and dynamic way recapitivated
on the inside in order for you to
control the outside and this and this of
course is is at the heart of early
formulations of things like the free
energy principle
in cybernetics you know Russia's good
regulative theorem would say literally a
thousand subsequent formulations in
terms of uh laws or acquisite variety
that the degrees of freedom on the
inside
um have to correspond to the degrees of
freedom on the things on the outside to
have to be controlled in the environment
and so I think I think that's absolutely
right that if you had already
established through having an internal
model of a particular Behavior a
particular way of deploying my actuators
and making sense of that and you know
being able to
um to infer it was me that did that and
this is me doing that and this is the
kind of thing that I do then you are in
a much stronger position to
um learn
um or incorporate or to imitate
um something that you have uh witnessed
to Novo
um and mathematically the reason why
that becomes easier
is the the
um the cost of belief updating in its
most General mathematical sense so I'm
not talking about personal beliefs I'm
just talking about any belief entail by
the structure the connectivity uh the
plasticity or indeed uh say neural
activity any belief updating comes along
with a cost
um and that cost is
um can be variously articulated in terms
of a failure to generalize
informationally uh thermodynamically it
has you know a cost uh via landauer's
principle
um but mathematically it's interesting
that it the cost is the relative entropy
between your prior and posterior beliefs
so this will be like a computational
cost a complexity cost
what that means is to make these steps
be they gradual or be they
um big jumps
um they can only be made
um if they're to use one of your words
um if they're
um they are suitably bounded in terms of
the complexity cost which means the
degree of belief updating literally the
relative entropy or the cow Divergence
between the implicit posterior and prior
after the update is sufficiently Smalls
which means literally you're changing
your mind in a sort of mathematical
sense in the most efficient way possible
so if you're already close to
um and have the right kind of generative
model to do imitation of a de novo
um behavior in Virtual the fact you've
done it before that means that the the
complexity cost of actually committing
to that and revising and belief updating
your generative model as now becomes
within a tenable range it becomes
acceptable so that you know that would
certainly make sense if I was simulating
that
um and um you know we've been talking
about ways of um all sorts of different
questions expressions in the chat that
you know these questions
um
um and The Plea um from Michael you know
how would you make this Mechanics Work
in terms of resolving various hypotheses
and um
um invincing insights into how all of
this works I think at the end of the day
you're going to have to simulate it
um and
um you know there's this a couple of uh
this has not been done very much in the
setting of the free energy principle or
active infant certainly but they're now
are a number of papers coming out within
the past year or a few months and uh you
know it might be interesting to go to
those and I'm thinking of uh for example
um a paper by Casper hesp's group that
looked I think the final write-up is
something like one small step for
mankind or something but it was
originally entitled um ideas worth
spreading so it's explicitly using the
Bayesian mechanics of belief updating to
look at how
um how spreadable
how copyable certain
um certain beliefs were
um
framed in the in the current age of the
internet and sort of tweet tweets and
the like and the same kind of theme has
also been taken up by uh colleagues of
Conor Heinz and Maxwell Randstad in
terms of
um simulating epistemic communities
where coming back to Michael's use of
the uh you know the importance of
epistemic spread and copying uh video
and imitation being basically an
epistemic spread that's now starting to
be simulated so I think we are on the
cusp in the world of active inference at
least on having
um
mechanics out there that's actually
realized in silica that you can start to
intervene on and model things of this
kind of that kind and speaking to Dean's
question earlier on you know it strikes
me that the people in climatology must
face exactly the same problem is this
missing data or did this thing actually
go away and of course it's a really
important uh really important question
to answer then in principle you could do
it if you've got a model of those Legacy
data you have to have a model which
means you've got to basically have an in
silicone
um sort of digital twin of the way you
think it works and then you can compare
two generative models or digital twins
on the way it works and see which has
the greatest evidence in light of the
historical data that clearly hasn't been
done either in climate change or or or
or your field but in principle that
would be the way to you know way to do
that I'm sorry I've gone over time sorry
it's totally fine Carl my my reflection
on that as we again anyone else who
wants to have any last um words is in
the par at all 2022 textbook there's
attention to two kinds of surprise
plain surprise which is an information
theoretic quality quantity associated
with an observation with respect to its
prior
and the second being Bayesian surprise
which is what you just described the uh
cost of movements which is the related
to the Divergence of movements and I
think in that difference between
that was surprising
and I surprised me
or I have changed
are two aspects of
the scenario
because to just be surprised
doesn't require one to change at all
one can just say every day wake up check
the news I can't believe that they're
doing that you can just be surprised
again and again
and then there's the Bayesian surprise
with the belief updating and that is
really where the semantic
advances
of the Bayesian mechanics are just
beginning to mature
I I hate the last word but and I hope it
isn't
um so the propagations have been dropped
in 53.0 and 53.1 and um Daniel and Dean
have avoided being provocateurs so far
um what I'm really looking forward to is
in 53.2 whether we can declare game on
because I think if we do if we have that
to look forward to we can push the
narrative to the end of the timetable
and we can start to or continue to
enhance the conversation that we
initiated today so I just want to say
thank you to all of you for all of the
uh the care and the passion that you um
shared with us and I'm just I'm just
happy as can be so thank you
thank you any final comments Hector
Michael
no just thank you for having us and
sharing this time with us I mean it was
being great discussion thank you
well thank you very much
uh it's been most most profitable
session
excellent
Carl any last thoughts
again this I've enjoyed it greatly
um and you know it's a real pleasure to
actually speak to yeah to all of you but
in particular uh Michael and Hector
you're actually using words that's
spoken words very embodied very natural
lovely
excellent all right till next time thank
you everybody
bye